<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-zhu-rmcat-framework-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
     full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="RMCAT framework">Framework for Real-time Media Congestion
    Avoidance Techniques</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Xianqing Zhu" initials="X" surname="Zhu">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12515 Research Blvd., Building 4</street>

          <city>Austin</city>

          <region>TX</region>

          <code>78759</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>xiaoqzhu@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker" initials="Z." surname="Sarker">
      <organization>Ericsson AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Luleae</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>00 46 10 717 37 43</phone>

        <email>zaheduzzaman.sarker@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="02" month="July" year="2016" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
     in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>RMCAT WG</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
     IETF is fine for individual submissions.
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
     which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>RTP</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
     files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
     output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
     keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>Congestion control is an essential element in ensuring fair bandwidth
      usage and preventing congestion collapse for traffic sharing the
      Internet. For interactive real-time media traffic such as video
      conferencing, design of congestion control solution also needs to
      account for many other factors such as the requirement for low latency
      packet delivery and interactions with live video encoder. This document
      describes a common framework with the core functional building blocks
      for a real-time media congestion solutions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Given increasing amount of interactive real-time media traffic over
      the Internet, such as video conferencing, it is important that these
      applications employ proper congestion control mechanisms to avoid
      congestion collapse. <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-cc-requirements"></xref> specifies the list of
      requirements of a viable solution.</t>

      <t>This document outlines a common framework for designing a congestion
      control mechanism for real-time interactive communication. [ Editor's
      note : This document does not describe the interaction between
      application , codec and congestion control system. The interaction among
      application, codec and congestion control system are define in other
      documents. There is a possibility to merge all the documents into one
      single document. ]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Key Words for Requirements">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Functional Modules">
      <t>A viable solution for real-time media congestion control needs to
      comprise of several common modules. This section provides a brief
      description of them and their respective functionalities. A congestion
      control solution for real-time media should comprise of the described
      functional modules. This should help understanding different congestion
      control solutions.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Network Congestion Controller : this is the core module for
          estimating available bandwidth over the network based on periodic
          RTCP feedback reports <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> from the
          receiver. Input of this module include periodic RTCP feedback
          reports as well as shared states of other flows in the same
          application sharing the same transport bottleneck. Output of this
          module is the estimated available bandwidth. This module contains
          key functions and calculations required to detect congestion and
          estimate available bandwidth on the transmission path based on the
          receiption quality of the media traffic. Different congestion
          control solutions employ different algorithms in detecting
          congestion and estimating available bandwidth for its media flow. It
          also possible that multiple media streams are multiplexed over a
          single transport, hence share the same congestion control module in
          aggregation.</t>

          <t>Transmission Queue : this module is needed to absorb the
          instantaneous mismatch between output from a live video encoder and
          regulated outgoing traffic. The transmission queue schedules
          outgoing traffic according to sending rate recommended by a rate
          controller module. It reports back its occupancy level to the rate
          controller module to assist the future rate control decisions on
          target video rate, sending rate, and probing rate.</t>

          <t>Rate Controller : this module takes the estimated available
          bandwidth from the network congestion control module, shared states
          of other flows, as well as occupancy level of the transmission queue
          as input. It makes holistic decisions on: a) target video rate for
          the live video encoder; b) sending rate for regulating outgoing
          traffic for the transmission queue; and c) rate of probing packets
          when needed. In the case where multiple media streams share a single
          transport and a common network congestion controller (for estimating
          available bandwidth in aggregation), the controller is also
          responsible for distributing available bandwidth amongst different
          media streams according to their relative priorities and based on
          shared state information.</t>

          <t>Network Probe : A congestion control solution can use probing to
          estimate the available bandwidth on the media transmission path.
          This can be specially effective when increasing the transmission
          rate. The solution can use different techniques for probing the
          network - for example it can use simple dummy packet with unknown
          payload type or use Forward Error Correction (FEC) packets. The
          network probe module is responsible for such packet generation.
          While this document does not specify what probing technique to use
          or how those packets should be generated, a complete congestion
          control solution needs to specify total rate of the probe packets to
          the rate controller module.</t>

          <t>Live Video Encoder : the sender typically also contains a live
          video encoder, which adjusts the its encoding parameters according
          to the target video rate set by the rate controller. The output rate
          from the video encoder may deviate from this target due to
          uncertainty in the captured video content characteristics and the
          encoder rate control process. Note that internal operations of the
          video encoder (i.e., how video encoder rate control works) is out of
          scope for this document. </t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example Configurations">
      <section anchor="subsec-config-single-stream"
               title="Example Configurations for a Single Stream">
        <t><figure anchor="fig-rmcat-solution-framework"
            title="RMCAT Solution Framework at the Sender: Single Stream">
            <artwork><![CDATA[

                                                   RTCP Feedback
+---------+                       +-------------+   Reports
|  Live   |                       |   Network   |<---------------- 
|  Video  |<----------------+     |  Congestion |
| Encoder |                 |     |  Controller |<------+
+---------+                 |     +-------------+       |  Shared
    ||                      |            |(1)           |  States
    ||                      |            |              +----------  
    ||                      |           \|/             |
    ||    +--------------+  |  (4) +-------------+      |
    ||    |   Network    |  +------|    Rate     |<-----+    
    ||    |    probe     |<--------| Controller  | 
    ||    |              |    (5)  +-------------+
    ||    +--------------+          (3)|   /|\ 
    ||           ||                    |    |
    ||           || FEC/Padding       \|/   |(2)         
    ||           || Packets       +---------------+   
    ||           \\=============> |  Transmission | 
    \\==========================> |      Queue    |==============>
        Encoded Video Packets     +---------------+   Outgoing  
                                                       Packets     
                
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><xref target="fig-rmcat-solution-framework"></xref> shows an
        example configuration at the sender for supporting a single media
        stream. The Network Congestion Controller estimates available
        bandwidth based on periodic RTCP feedback reports and shared states
        about other streams. The Rate Controller takes the estimated available
        bandwidth (1) , the current occupancy level of the Transmission Queue
        (2), as well as the shared states on other flows as inputs and
        calculates sending rate (3) for the Transmission Queue. It then
        distributes the sending rate between the live video encoder as target
        encoding rate (4), and rate of probe packets (5) if they are needed.
        The Transmission Queue holds output packets from both the Live Video
        Encoder and the Network Probe, and regulates its outgoing traffic
        according to the sending rate (3) specified by Rate Controller.</t>

        <t>Obviously, it is possible for a congestion control solution to
        contain alternative configurations (wirings) between the functional
        modules. It is required that the candidate solution draft specify how
        they align to this framework.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="subsec-config-multiple-streams"
               title="Example Configurations for Multiple Streams">
        <t><figure anchor="fig-rmcat-solution-multi-stream"
            title="RMCAT Solution Framework at the Sender: Multiple Streams">
            <artwork><![CDATA[  

                                                   RTCP Feedback
+---------+                       +-------------+   Reports
|  Live   |                       |   Network   |<---------------- 
|  Video  |<----------------+     |  Congestion |
| Encoder |                 |     |  Controller |<------+
+---------+                 |     +-------------+       |  Shared
    ||                      |            |(1)           |  States
    ||                      |            |              +----------  
    ||                      |           \|/             |
    ||                      |  (4) +-------------+      |
    ||      +---------+     +------|    Rate     |<-----+    
    ||      |  Live   |     |      | Controller  | 
    ||      |  Video  |<----+      +-------------+
    ||      | Encoder |             (3)|   /|\ 
    ||      +---------+                |    |
    ||          ||                    \|/   |(2)         
    ||          ||                +---------------+   
    ||          ||                |  Transmission | 
    \\==========================> |      Queue    |==============>
        Encoded Video Packets     +---------------+   Outgoing  
                                                       Packets     
          
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><xref target="fig-rmcat-solution-multi-stream"></xref> shows an
        example configuration for multiple video streams sharing a common
        Network Congestion Controller. The Network Congestion Controller
        calculates an aggregated estimated available bandwidth (1) based on
        periodic RTCP feedback reports and Shared States. Based on such
        information and occupancy level of the transmission queue for each sub
        stream (2), the Rate Controller divides up the aggregate estimated
        bandwidth amongst sub-streams based on their relative priority levels,
        and subsequently regulates the sending rate of each Transmission Queue
        (3), target video rate (4). For sake of simplicity the role of network
        probe is omitted in the above figure.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The RMCAT design team discussions contributed to this memo.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-cc-requirements"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3550"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3551"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4585"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5104"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0768"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
